Guide to the Fairhaven United Methodist Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1900-1993 AIS.1993.12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Fairhaven United Methodist Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1900-1993
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Fairhaven United Methodist Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1993.12
2 microfilm_reels (1365 frames; negative and positive)
This collection contains records of baptisms, marriages, members, funerals, deaths, removals, a minutebook, financial records, and pictures of the church and ministers of the Fairhaven United Methodist Church, Pittsburgh, Pa., 1900-1993.
History
The Fairhaven United Methodist Church is located at 2415 Saw Mill Run Boulevard on route 51 in the Overbrook section of Pittsburgh. It began in 1881 when a man by the name of Perry was converted while attending a camp meeting in Castle Shannon. Perry believed that the community of Overbrook needed religious services so he organized a Sunday School. In 1883, the Pittsburgh Conference of the Methodist Protestant Church appointed Reverend Samuel F. Crowther pastor of the Fairhaven Mission. On August 31, 1884 the Mission was formally organizedas the Fairhaven Methodist Protestant Church. The first church was built in 1890 on Glenbury Street on a lot donated by Robert Thompson. The present church, located on a lot donated by the J.F. Horning family, was dedicated on December 8, 1907. At that time the church was under the leadership of Reverend C.S. Sanders. In 1940, a renovation was begun and the cost was liquidated by February 24, 1946. In 1968, the membership of the church was 334.
Scope and Content
This collection contains records of the Fairhaven United Methodist Church, Pittsburgh, PA, 1900-1993. The records are arranged into 6 books. Books 1-4 contain baptisms, marriages, members, funerals, deaths, and removals. Book 5 includes a minute book of the Auxilliary Branch of the Allegheny County Sabbath School Association from a convention of the Sabbath Schools of the northern part of Baldwin Township and the borough of Knoxville. Book 5 also contains financial records (1899-1902) that include pastor subscriptions, envelope accounts, and basket collection account. Book 6 includes pictures of ministers, ministerial records, pictures of church.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were a gift of Fairhaven United Methodist Church, 2415 Saw Mill Run Blvd., Pittsburgh, Pa. 1993.
Existence and Location of Originals
This collection has been microfilmed by Archives of Industrial Society from originals in the possession of the Fairhaven United Methodist Church, 2415 Saw Mill Run Blvd., Pittsburgh, Pa.
Previous Citation
Fairhaven United Methodist Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, AIS.1993.12, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Fairhaven United Methodist Church, Pittsburgh, PA., Records, 1900-1993, ais 93:12, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries.
Church records; Baptismal records -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Marriage records; Death records; Overbrook (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Church history; Church buildings -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Churches and Synagogues; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Church history; United Methodist Church (U.S.) -- Clergy; Fairhaven United Methodist Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Book 1
  - Baptisms, Members, Marriages, 1900-1923 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 1, Item 1)
- Book 2
  - Members, Marriages, Baptisms, 1924-1929 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 1, Item 2)
- Book 3
  - Members, Marriages, Baptisms, Funerals, 1939-1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 1, Item 3)
- Book 4A
  - Members, Baptisms, Preparatory Members, Deaths, Removals (A-B), 1959-1993 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 1, Item 4)
- Book 4B
  - Removals (C-G), 1959-1993 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 1, Item 5)
  - Removals (H-Z), 1959-1993 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 2, Item 1)
- Book 5
  - Minute Book, September 9, 1897 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 2, Item 2)
  - Financial Records, 1899-1902 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 2, Item 3)
- Book 6
  - Pictures of Ministers, Ministerial Records, Pictures of Church, no date (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 2, Item 4)